Guide to the Baptist Theological Union Records 1863-1999
University of Chicago Library
Baptist Theological Union. Records
1863-1999
35 linear feet (34 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The collection contains records of the Baptist Theological Union, including minutes and administrative records, correspondence, financial information, and news clippings, documenting the early history of the B.T.U. and the activities of its governing board and committees.
Information on Use
Access
Series III contains administrative and financial records that are restricted for fifty years from the date of creation. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Historical Note
In August 1863 a group of Baptist leaders met in Chicago and created the Baptist Theological Union. On Feb. 16, 1865, the Illinois legislature granted the Baptist Theological Union a charter for "the founding, endowment, support, and direction of an institution for theological instruction." That same year, Dr. Nathaniel Colver began to give instruction to a few students in his study. The Baptist Union Theological Seminary fully launched in 1866.
The formal work of the Baptist Union Theological Seminary began with the appointment of George W. Northrup as President and Professor of Systematic Theology. In the fall of 1867, courses in that subject as well as Ecclesiastical History and Biblical Literature and Exegesis were given to nineteen students in the Old University of Chicago’s Douglas Hall. On July 1, 1869, the Seminary dedicated its own building directly across the street from the Old University of Chicago. The Seminary provided theological education in English, Norwegian, Swedish, and Danish to Old University of Chicago and non-University students. Facing financial hardship in the mid-1870s, the Seminary sold its buildings near the Old University of Chicago and moved to donated land in the Chicago suburb of Morgan Park in 1877. The Old University of Chicago closed in 1886.
When John D. Rockefeller donated money toward the founding of the new University of Chicago, he made it a condition of the gift that the Baptist Union Theological Seminary become the Divinity School of the new institution. This took place formally on July 1, 1892. Since the establishment of the University of Chicago Divinity School, the Baptist Theological Union has continued its existence as a separate organization with its own Board, overseeing an endowment that provides support to the Divinity School.
Many Baptist Theological Union and Baptist Union Theological Seminary leaders were key to the founding and early history of the University of Chicago. E. Nelson Blake, President of the Board of the Baptist Theological Union from 1877 to 1893, was also a major donor to the new University of Chicago, and the first chairman of the University’s Board of Trustees. Edward Goodman and Thomas W. Goodspeed were also active in both institutions. The University of Chicago’s first President, William R. Harper, was a professor of Hebrew and Cognate Languages in the Seminary from 1879 to 1886. Dr. Eri B. Hulbert joined the faculty of the Seminary in 1881. In 1892, he became the first Dean of the Divinity School (until 1907).
Scope Note
The material in this collection has been organized into three series. Series I includes materials documenting the founding and early history of the B.T.U., including it’s relationship with the University of Chicago. It includes correspondence, financial records, minutes, and reports. Series II documents the operations and governance of the B.T.U. from 1928 through the 1960s, and consists primarily of records relating to the organizations annual meeting and meetings of the Board of Trustees. Series III contains records similar to those in Series II, dating from the 1960s to the 1990s. Access to these records is restricted for fifty years from the date of creation, because they contain materials relating to the financial and personnel affairs of the B.T.U.
The early records of the B.T.U. previously formed parts of the collection “Baptist Theological Union and Baptist Union Theological Seminary. Records.”
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
University of Chicago. Divinity School. Records
Baptist Union Theological Seminary. Records
Subject Headings
University of Chicago (1857-1866); University of Chicago. Divinity School; Baptist Theological Union (Chicago, Ill.); Baptist Union Theological Seminary (Morgan Park, Ill.)
INVENTORY
- Series I: Baptist Theological Seminary, Founding and Early Administration, 1863-1927
  - An Act to Incorporate the Baptist Theological Union, located in Chicago" (1865); By-Laws of the Board of Trustees (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Memorandum of the Baptist Theological Union of Chicago." Notes and records taken by G.S. Bailey, Financial and Recording Secretary [1867-75]. Includes B.T.U. Board of Trustees minutes 1867 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1897-1900 [T.W. Goodspeed, Secy.] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1902-1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1904-1907 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1907-1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes of the Board of Trustees, 1902-1910, mimeographed (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1874 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., 1877-1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., March, 1880 – November, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., December, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., January, 1902 – March, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., April, 1912 – November, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Annual Reports of the Board of Trustees of the B.T.U., 1871, 1891-1892; 1895-1904 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Special Committee Reports, circa 1875-1909 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Commission to Study the Relations of the B.T.U. and the Scandinavian Theological Seminary at Morgan Park, correspondence, notes and report, 1888-1912 (Box 2, Folder 8A)
  - Early Reports of the B.T.U. at the time of Union with University of Chicago, 1891-1908 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Agreements between the Baptist Theological Union and the University of Chicago, 1904-1908 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Commission on the Affairs of the Divinity School of the University of Chicago; Preliminary Report, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reports of Committees on Relation between the B.T.U. and the University of Chicago, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Contributors, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Memorandum of names of subscribers and amounts of subscriptions and donations for support and endowment of theological chair of N. Colver, DD. and successors, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1863-1870 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1866 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer’s book of the Ladies Baptist Education Society, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subscriptions of the Second Baptist Church of Chicago to the Theological Seminary Building, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subscriptions for a Theological Building, 2 vol., 1868 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Contributions, circa 1869-1872 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1873 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1875 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - G. A. Bailey, financial claims against the B.T.U., circa 1880 (Box 4, Folder 2A)
  - Subscriptions to the $100,000 endowment fund, circa 1882 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1884-1893 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1891 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer’s book, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1885-1901 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Financial Statements, 1901-1924 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports of the Treasurer, 1884-1924 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Accountant’s and Auditor’s Reports, 1885-1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Notes and reports on debts and investments, 1902-1912 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Real estate holdings, including Baptist Hospital, 1902-1922 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Treasurer, State of Illinois vs. the B.T.U., legal records 1897-1901 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ledger, 1895-1905 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook, News Clippings, April, 1876 – April, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, News Clippings, April, 1892 – March, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook, News Clippings, March, 1904 – March, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1914-1927, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1917-1927, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 7)
  - Historical volume, Records, v. 1, 1863-1899, Includes manuscript constitution, minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 8)
  - Historical volume, Records, v. 2, 1899-1917, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 9)
  - Historical volume, Records, 1863-1875, Includes manuscript constitution, minutes of annual meetings, Board of Trustees, and committes, duplicates records in Box 8 (Box 10)
  - Historical volume, Letters, 1913-1927, Includes carbon copies of outgoing correspondence of Secretary (Box 11)
  - Historical volume, Records, 1891, Includes agreement between B.T.U. and University of Chicago, letters from John D. Rockefeller (Box 12)
- Series II: Board of Trustees and Administrative Records, 1928-1962
  - Correspondence and administrative records, 1941-1953 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and administrative records, 1956-1958 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and administrative records, 1958-1962 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and administrative records, 1963-1966 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1953-1958 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1959-1960 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1960-1961 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1961-1963 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Annual meeting, notes and related documents, 1963-1964 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1928-1946, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 15)
  - Minutes, 1928-1946, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees, duplicates records in Box 15 (Box 16)
  - Minutes, 1931-1944, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 17)
  - Minutes, 1932-1946, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 18)
  - Minutes, 1943-1954, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 19)
  - Minutes, 1947-1954, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 20)
  - Minutes, 1947-1956, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 21)
  - Minutes, 1954-1958, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 22)
  - Minutes, 1957-1960, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 23)
  - Minutes, 1954-1957, 1958-1962, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 24)
  - Minutes, 1958-1962, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 25)
- Series III: Restricted Records, 1963-1999
  The records in this series are restricted for fifty years from the date of creation.
  - Minutes, 1963-1969, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 26)
  - Minutes, 1969-1980, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 27)
  - Minutes, 1980-1990, Includes minutes of annual meeting, Board of Trustees, and committees (Box 28)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1965-1967 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Administrative records, 1967-1969 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Administrative records, 1969-1971 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Trustees Meeting, October, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Trustees Meeting, April 19, 1972 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Administrative records, 1971-1972 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Administrative records, 1973-1974 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Financial Report, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 18, 1972 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 18, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 17, 1973 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 17, 1974 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 16, 1974 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Administrative records, 1974-1975 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 15, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 16, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Administrative records, 1975-1976 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 20, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 14, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 13, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 12, 1970 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Administrative records, 1977-1979 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Financial statements and records, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Financial statements and records, 1974 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Financial statements and records, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, October 19, 1977 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Administrative records, 1977-1978 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Administrative records, 1978-1981 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Administrative records, 1978-1980 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Dean’s Report to BTU, 1970-1973 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Dean’s Report to BTU, 1974-1979 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Administrative records, 1980-1982 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Administrative records, 1982-1983 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Administrative records, 1983-1984 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Administrative records, 1985-1986 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Administrative records, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Administrative records, 1986-1987 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Administrative records, 1987-1988 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Administrative records, 1988-1989 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Administrative records, 1989-1990 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Administrative records, 1990-1991 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Administrative records, 1991-1992 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Administrative records, 1992-1993 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Administrative records, 1993-1994 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Everett J. Tarbox, 1993-1995 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Administrative records, 1994-1995 (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Administrative records, 1995-1996 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Administrative records, 1995-1997 (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 18, 1996 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Annual meetings and Board of Trustees, April 10, 1997 and April 7, 1998 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, November 4, 1998 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - BTU Trustees Biographies, 1983-1998 (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Annual meeting and Board of Trustees, April 21, 1999 (Box 34, Folder 11)